Guide to the Stephen Gendin Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Stephen Gendin papers
1920-2000
MS 1963
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
10
(31 boxes)
This collection comprises the papers of HIV/AIDS activist and writer, Stephen Gendin. The materials document both Gendin's activism as well as his personal and family life, and include correspondence; photographs; writings; address and appointment books; student papers; notes; audio and video recordings; and electronic files. Many of the organizations with which Gendin was affiliated are represented in the collection, including the AIDS Coalition to Unleash Power (ACT UP); the AIDS Prevention Action League (APAL); Community Prescription Service (CPS); POZ Magazine; and Sex Panic!.
Gendin, Stephen, 1966-2000
Scope and Contents
This collection comprises the papers of HIV/AIDS activist and writer, Stephen Gendin. The materials document both Gendin's activism as well as his personal and family life, and include correspondence; photographs; writings; address and appointment books; student papers; notes; audio and video recordings; and electronic files. Many of the organizations with which Gendin was affiliated are represented in the collection, including the AIDS Coalition to Unleash Power (ACT UP); the AIDS Prevention Action League (APAL); Community Prescription Service (CPS); POZ Magazine; and Sex Panic!
Conditions Governing Access
The materials in Series I and II are open for research. Electronic files, in Series III are closed until processed.
Original audiovisual materials, as well as preservation and duplicating masters, may not be played. Researchers must consult use copies, or if none exist must pay for a use copy, which is retained by the repository. Researchers wishing to obtain an additional copy for their personal use should consult Copying Services information on the Manuscripts and Archives web site.
Biographical / Historical
Stephen Gendin, a prominent HIV/AIDS activist and writer, was born on February 20, 1966, and raised in Ypsilanti, Michigan. Growing up, Gendin was a straight-A student and was very active with the Boy Scouts of America, earning the distinction of National Explorer Scout of the Year as a teenager. He graduated as valedictorian of Ypsilanti High School in 1984, and attended college at Brown University.
During his freshman year at Brown, Gendin tested positive for HIV, which sparked his lifelong commitment to HIV/AIDS activism. He was an early member of the direct action advocacy group, AIDS Coalition to Unleash Power (ACT UP), founded in New York in 1987. Gendin served on ACT UP/New York's fundraising committee, and founded ACT UP/Rhode Island that same year. As a member of ACT UP, Gendin took part in a number of demonstrations and civil disobedience actions, and was arrested several times. Also in 1987, Gendin was selected as the youngest member of the executive committee of the National March on Washington for Lesbian and Gay Rights. In 1989, Gendin established ACT UP's Treatment and Data Digest, a pioneering newsletter designed to disseminate information on HIV/AIDS medications and treatments. That same year, Gendin completed a bachelor's degree in religious studies at Brown. He later completed two years toward a master's degree at the Union Theological Seminary.
During the 1990s, after a second large wave of HIV/AIDS infections impacted gay men, Gendin co-founded two advocacy organizations: the AIDS Prevention Action League (APAL), and Sex Panic!. These groups were formed largely in reaction to both mainstream political efforts and arguments within the gay community that promoted monogamy, the closing of sex clubs, and the demonization of public sex culture and promiscuity as the best ways to prevent HIV/AIDS. In contrast, these groups argued for the promotion of safe sex practices to prevent infection and against the shaming and marginalization of sexual practices that some considered deviant. During this time he also co-founded the Community Prescription Service, a mail-order business that sold FDA-approved prescription drugs to treat HIV/AIDS, in addition to disseminating information on new and upcoming treatments through newsletters and community forums.
Stephen Gendin achieved perhaps his greatest notoriety during the 1990s as a columnist for POZ Magazine, a publication devoted to documenting the HIV/AIDS epidemic and the lives of people affected by it. In his columns, Gendin wrote candidly about the struggles and indignities of living with and treating HIV and AIDS, and occasionally stirred controversy. Among Gendin's most infamous columns were one in which he discussed his conflicted feelings about knowingly engaging in unprotected sex after having been infected with HIV, and another in which he fantasized about assassinating US Senator Jesse Helms.
Throughout his adult life, Gendin tried various treatments and medications for HIV/AIDS as soon as they became available, but eventually the particular strain of the virus that had infected him became resistant to all medications. Stephen Gendin died of complications due to AIDS-related lymphoma on July 19, 2000.
Arrangement
The papers are arranged in three series: I. Personal papers. II. HIV/AIDS activism papers. III. Electronic files.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Kyle McDowell, 2010-2011.
AIDS (Disease) -- Prevention; AIDS (Disease) -- United States; AIDS activists; Gay activists; Gay men -- United States; Gendin, Stephen, 1966-2000; ACT UP (Organization)
- Personal papers, 1920s-2000; Series I
  Conditions Governing Access
  Original audiovisual materials, as well as preservation and duplicating masters, may not be played. Researchers must consult use copies, or if none exist must pay for a use copy, which is retained by the repository. Researchers wishing to obtain an additional copy of non-commercially produced items for their personal use should consult Copying Services information on the Manuscripts and Archives web site.
  Scope and Contents
  This series comprises a variety of materials documenting Stephen Gendin's personal and family life from his childhood until his death at age 34. Correspondence in the series consists of letters written to Gendin by friends, partners, lovers, and relatives. Gendin's journals and personal writings provide great insight into his formative teenage and early adult years, particularly his coming out and identity as a gay man. In his early journals, Gendin writes about coming out to his family and friends during high school, as well as his experiences and feelings about being an openly gay teenager during the early 1980s. During his teenage years, Gendin also started writing frankly in his journal about his own sexuality and sexual experiences, a theme that would eventually carry over into his work for POZ Magazine, where he was known for often writing candidly about his sex life. In Gendin's Sex Journal, compiled during the late-1990s, he individually lists and describes most, if not all of his sexual encounters and partners dating back to 1982. After high school, Gendin's journal writing became more inconsistent. In journals dating from his college years, Gendin writes primarily about romantic and sexual experiences, his studies, and makes only occasional references to his contraction of HIV and his increasing involvement in HIV/AIDS activism. Only a few pages of journal writing from his post-college years are included in the papers. Also included in Gendin's personal writings are poems that he wrote for Kyle "Hush" McDowell, his partner from 1996 until his death; an essay on an experience at a gay dance club called The Saint; and a piece titled "Unnamed Magazine," which is handwritten and roughly laid out like a magazine, but does not appear to be a template for an actual publication. Gendin's student files include papers and assignments completed while he was a student at Ypsilanti High School, at Brown University, and during his graduate studies at the Union Theological Seminary. Also included are copies of Gendin's college applications; awards and scholarships he received when he graduated high school; college transcripts; and papers related to job searches both during and right after college. Photographs in the collection date primarily from the 1990s, and consist mostly of snapshots of Gendin and his friends at social functions, and on vacations and trips abroad. Some of these photographs appear to have been taken at Gay Pride events in New York City. There are also a number of nude photographs of Gendin, many of which appear to be self-portraits, and some of which feature vivid depictions of sexual acts.
  Family photographs in the collection include a Gendin family photograph album as well as some loose photographs. There are many photographs of Stephen Gendin, his sister, Margo, and his parents dating from his childhood. There are also a number of photographs of Gendin's parents dating back to their childhoods, as well as photographs of other relatives dating back to the 1920s. Gendin's personal papers also include audio recordings of some of his outgoing telephone answering machine messages. Gendin was known by his family, friends and colleagues for recording lengthy, stream-of-consciousness outgoing messages that featured updates on his life and other musings.
  Lastly, Stephen Gendin's personal papers feature a variety of materials related to his death, including copies of his death certificate and will; sympathy cards, letters, and print-outs of emails sent to Gendin's partner, Hush McDowell; materials from Gendin's memorial service, including a guestbook; and several copies of the October 2000 issue of POZ Magazine, which was dedicated to Gendin's memory. The issue featured five different covers with photographs of Gendin, as well as written tributes by many of his friends and colleagues.
  - Correspondence, 1982-1999
    - General, 1984-1996 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Ankenbrandt, Bill, 1986 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Archimandritis, George, 1994 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Aurigemma, Mark, 1987 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Auterman, John, 1985 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Ayres, Lynn, 1984-1987, 1999 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Budo, Michael A., 1993 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Carrier, Daniel, 1985-1986 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Cregan, Tom, 1987-1991 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Fellis, Michael, 1994 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Fullerton, Nils
      - 1986-1993 (Box 1, Folder 11-12)
      - 1986-1991 (Box 2, Folder 1-4)
    - Gannon, Paul, 1984-1985 (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - Geherin, Chris, 1987-1988 (Box 3, Folder 2)
    - Gendin, Margo, 1988 (Box 3, Folder 3)
    - Gendin, Natalie, 1984-1989 (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - Gendin, Sidney, 1990-1997 (Box 3, Folder 5)
    - Gindin, Jay, Undated (Box 3, Folder 6)
    - Girbach, Darryl, 1986, 1989 (Box 3, Folder 7)
    - Greenburg, Dan, Undated (Box 3, Folder 8)
    - Harmon, Jacob, 1984-1992 (Box 3, Folder 9)
    - Hauser, G., 1984-1986 (Box 3, Folder 10)
    - Hoffman, Jennifer, 1986, 1989 (Box 3, Folder 11)
    - Jesdale, Bill, 1989 (Box 3, Folder 12)
    - Kassarjian, Steve, 1985-1987 (Box 3, Folder 13)
    - Kraft, Joe, 1984, 1986 (Box 3, Folder 14)
    - LaSaine, John, 1986 (Box 3, Folder 15)
    - Lázaro, Gina, 1984-1985 (Box 3, Folder 16)
    - Lohmeier (Lundquist), Cindy, 1984-1988 (Box 3, Folder 17)
    - Lyons, Jess, 1984 (Box 3, Folder 18)
    - Ossenheimer, Mark, 1991-1992 (Box 4, Folder 1)
    - Paluchniak, Thomas, 1986-1988 (Box 4, Folder 2)
    - Parish, David, 1985-1987 (Box 4, Folder 3)
    - Raynsford, Tony, 1987 (Box 4, Folder 4)
    - Rehfuss, Todd, 1984-1986 (Box 4, Folder 5)
    - Rudy, Joe, 1989 (Box 4, Folder 6)
    - Salhany, Richard, 1986-1987 (Box 4, Folder 7)
    - Thurston, Regina, 1984-1986 (Box 4, Folder 8)
    - Turrentine, Sarah, 1985 (Box 4, Folder 9)
    - Valenzuela, Tony, 1998 (Box 4, Folder 10)
    - Whalen, Larry, 1982 (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - Journals and personal writings
    - Journals
      - 1982-1988 (Box 5, Folder 1-4)
      - 1992, 1994, undated (Box 5, Folder 5)
      - Sex journal, 1982-1999 (Box 5, Folder 6)
    - Poetry for Hush, Undated (Box 5, Folder 7)
    - The Saint, 1987, undated (Box 5, Folder 8)
    - Unnamed magazine, Undated (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - Student files
    - High school, 1981-1984 (Box 6, Folder 1)
    - Awards and scholarships, 1984 (Box 6, Folder 2)
    - College applications, 1984 (Box 6, Folder 3)
    - Brown University, 1985-1989 (Box 6, Folder 4-7)
    - Job search, 1986-1989 (Box 6, Folder 8)
    - Brown University diploma, 1989 (Box 7, Folder 1)
    - Brown University Lesbian and Gay Student Alliance, 1984, 1988 (Box 7, Folder 2)
    - Union Theological Seminary, 1993 (Box 7, Folder 3-4)
  - Stephen Gendin's death
    - Death certificate, 2000 (Box 8, Folder 1)
    - E-mails to Hush regarding Stephen's death, 2000-2002 (Box 8, Folder 2)
    - Memorial service
      - Guest book and ephemera, 2000 (Box 8, Folder 3)
      - Video recording, 2000; 2 (Box 21–22)
    - POZ Magazine, Stephen Gendin memorial issue, 2000 (Box 8, Folder 4)
    - Sympathy cards and correspondence, 2000 (Box 8, Folder 5-6)
    - Stephen Gendin's will, 2000 (Box 8, Folder 7)
  - Photographs
    - General
      - Circa 1985-1989 (Box 9, Folder 1-6)
      - 1990s (Box 10, Folder 1-5)
      - 1990s (Box 11, Folder 1-3)
      - Oversize, Circa 1985-1989 (Box 12, Folder 2)
    - Gendin family
      - 1920s-1980s (Box 11, Folder 4-5)
      - Album, 1920s-1980s (Box 12, Folder 1)
  - Audio recordings
    - Answering machine message, 1990
      - Original recording, 1 (Box 23)
      - Use copy, 1 (Box 23U)
    - Answering machine messages, 2000, undated
      - Original recordings, 2 (Box 24–25)
      - Use copies (Box 24U–25U)
- HIV/AIDS activism papers, 1987-2000; Series II
  HIV/AIDS activism papers document various aspcects of Stephen Gendin's career as an advocate for HIV/AIDS awareness and treatment. Clippings in the collection date mostly from the late 1980s and document direct action protests organized by the AIDS Coalition to Unleash Power (ACT UP), many of which Gendin participated in. Relatedly, the papers also include records pertaining to Gendin's several arrests for civil disobedience actions as a member of ACT UP. These arrests occured mostly at protests in New York City and the Washington, DC area. The papers also include several years' worth of address and appointment books, both of which are illustrative of Gendin's day-to-day work life, as well as the network he cultivated and utilized as an activist.
  The largest single body of documents in this series consists of handwritten notes by Gendin, written mostly on yellow legal pads. The notes date primarily from the 1990s, and though Gendin's note-taking style and organizational structure were highly idiosyncratic, the content of the notes suggests that they mostly relate to his work with POZ Magazine and the Community Prescription Service (CPS). The notes, in fact, contain the most extensive documentation of CPS contained in the collection, detailing its development and day-to-day operations. There are also a great many notes related to HIV/AIDS-related issues whose context within the scope of Gendin's work is not readily discernible.
  Lastly, the series includes files pertaining to HIV/AIDS activist organizations with which Gendin was affiliated. The types of documents contained in these files include fliers; clippings; newsletters; meeting minutes and agendas; contact lists, audio and video recordings; and correspondence.
  - General
    - Clippings, 1987-1999 (Box 13, Folder 1)
    - Civil disobedience arrest records, 1987-1990 (Box 13, Folder 2)
    - "My Hero! Honoring Stephen Gendin to Benefit Aid for AIDS" promotional materials, 2000 (Box 13, Folder 3)
    - Sexually Transmitted Diseases (STD) awareness pamphlets and ephemera, Circa 1990s (Box 13, Folder 4-6)
  - Address books, Undated (Box 14, Folder 1-2)
  - Appointment books
    - 1992-1993 (Box 14, Folder 3)
    - 1994-2000, undated (Box 15, Folder 1-8)
  - Notes, 1990s (Box 16, Folder 1-6)
  - Notes, 1990s (Box 17, Folder 1-5)
  - Organizations
    - AIDS Coalition to Unleash Power (ACT-UP), 1987-1988 (Box 18, Folder 1)
    - AIDS Prevention Action League (APAL), 1995 (Box 18, Folder 2-5)
    - Community AIDS Prevention Activists (CAPA), 1995 (Box 18, Folder 6)
    - Community Prescription Service (CPS), 1994-1999 (Box 18, Folder 7)
    - National March on Washington for Lesbian and Gay Rights, Executive Board, 1987 (Box 18, Folder 8-9)
    - National March on Washington for Lesbian and Gay Rights, Executive Board, 1987 (Box 19, Folder 1)
    - New York City HIV Prevention Plan, report and research materials, 1995 (Box 19, Folder 2)
    - New York City Prevention Planning Group
      - Men who have sex with men (MSM) working group, research materials and draft reports, 1995-1996 (Box 19, Folder 3)
      - Men who have sex with men (MSM) and women who have sex with women (WSW) working group, contacts list, 1996 (Box 19, Folder 4)
    - Northeast Gay and Lesbian Student Union
      - Conference, Columbia University, 1987 March 29; 1 (Box 26)
      - Conference; New York City Hall demonstration, 1989; "The Redemption of Joey"; New York City Gay Pride Parade, 1987-1991; 1 (Box 27)
    - POZ Magazine articles and correspondence, 1999-2000, undated (Box 20, Folder 1)
    - Sean Strub for Congress
      - Sean Strub for Congress television advertisements, 1 (Box 28)
    - Sex Panic!
      - Articles and correspondence, 1995-1999, undated (Box 20, Folder 2-4)
      - Capri Theater closing testimony, 1995 (Box 20, Folder 5)
      - Event fliers, 1997-1998, undated (Box 20, Folder 6)
      - Mailing lists, 1997, undated (Box 20, Folder 7)
      - New York City sex club closings, 1995 (Box 20, Folder 8)
      - PSA scripts and plans, 1995 (Box 20, Folder 9)
      - Rotello, Gabriel, controversy, 1996 (Box 20, Folder 10)
      - S&M community information and news, 1997 (Box 20, Folder 11)
      - Summit, San Diego, 1997 (Box 20, Folder 12)
      - Summit, San Diego, sexuality forum, 1997
        - Original recording, 1 (Box 29)
        - Use copy, 2 (Box 29Ua–29Ub)
      - Survey, 1997 (Box 20, Folder 13)
      - Teach-in, 1997; 2 (Box 30–31)
- Electronic files, Circa 1985-2000; Series III (Box 32–33)
  This accession consists of twenty-six 3.5" floppy disks, three 5.25" floppy disks, one CD-R, and one 5.25" SyQuest disk cartridge.
  Closed until processed.